<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://theohenson.com/</id>
  <title>Theo Henson's blog and poems</title>
  <updated>2023-08-26T05:32:24.874403+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Theo Henson</name>
    <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://theohenson.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>Miscellaneous writings.</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/poems.html#2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</id>
    <title>New poems published</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[Poems are published on a single, rolling page at <a href="https://theohenson.com/poems.html">theohenson.com/poems.html</a>]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/poems.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-zuckerberg.html</id>
    <title>Zuckerberg</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Zuckerberg">Zuckerberg</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-10-14</p>
<p>The boy was born in 1984 (the year that the thing named after the apple was released) in a suburb of the Big City.
He afforded a lucky childhood in a typical way: excelling at the various academies he attended, instilling pride in his family.
Enamored with some normal things, he liked the movies, but also enjoyed mathematics and ancient literature.
Most of all, though, it was the computer that occupied his time.
He used it to build machines—machines that didn’t have motors or wires, rather loops and logic: programs.
Programs that talked to each other, played games and music, all without needing physical parts replaced or repaired—they were beautiful machines.</p>
<p>Eventually, the boy lived up to the grandeur of his youth and was accepted to the University (the same university where that president—and the other one—had gone).
He made more programs there, just for fun. After all, it was what his classes were about.
These programs, though, dealt with people, and people used them too.
They were used enough that he started to take things seriously: he made a company.
In a way, this was a new machine, one built with people and money.
He wanted to use this machine to spread the joys of his programs past the gated grounds of the University;
he wanted the world to be improved, but didn’t know if he was the one to do it.</p>
<p>The boy saw an opportunity, and so he took it. He left the University to build the Machine (the Machine was both a program and a company, but in a way, more than the sum of its parts).
He got the money from prospectors in the Valley who now looked not for gold, but for golden ideas.
The people came naturally because they liked the Machine—at this point it was very likable—it was charming, fun, even.
People who knew those people came to the Machine, their friends and family.
Word of it spread quickly: “a wonderful machine full of things made by people you know,” and the boy worked hard to meet this ideal.
He was quite happy with what he accomplished.
He had lived up to and beyond the grandeur that even the University would have expected of him. He had become popular with the people and made a comfortable living.
These were all things he was told he should want, but most importantly, he was happy that the programs he made were now part of the world.</p>
<hr/>
<p>The Machine was marvelous, of course, but it could not be stopped (because now it was the sum of a program, a company, and hundreds of millions of people and even more dollars).
The boy went along with this, but really, the Machine went along, while he just followed.
He tried to make more programs, just for fun, but it swallowed them.
The Machine was terribly hungry; it ate his time and his humanity—when it needed more fuel, it ate those of the people.</p>
<p>The boy saw as strange things started to come to the Machine (it permitted these things, as the Machine was indiscriminate in who could use it, so long as it could extract fuel).
Strange things made by corporations, governments, other machines—not people.
They tricked the people with the Machine’s own functions; manipulated them to siphon fuel for themselves.
The Machine was no longer a part of the world; it was a world unto itself—a world where people and Things fought, the Machine monitoring all of them, all the time.
He was belted to the driver’s seat and the controls were ripped out.</p>
<p>The Things changed the boy. He needed his machine to cooperate with them (the Machine was what gave him purpose, it was the only anchor he had in life, and it must keep running).
As it grew bigger he became increasingly dissociated. Now, he was no boy.
To the people, he was the man who ran the Machine—the Machine they hated to love but loved nonetheless.
To himself, he did not know. All he saw were the loops and logic, the people and money.
For many of the people, the world that the Machine provided was more of a world than the real one.
It was no longer likable, charming, or fun, but the people still loved it—they needed to.
They could not imagine life without it.</p>
<hr/>
<p>The man often asked himself if he had actually improved the world.
Of course, it didn’t really matter: nothing could be changed.
He realized now that he was dead, buried deep within the programming.
Whatever was left of him was used by the Machine to talk to different Things which stood in its way—the direction it took changed with each passing month, and the people changed with it.
Unguided, the Machine now existed just to exist; it, its own anchor, so it must keep running.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-zuckerberg.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-three-poems.html</id>
    <title>Three Poems</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Three%20Poems">Three Poems</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-02-15</p>
<h3 id="Pax%20Americana">Pax Americana</h3>
<pre><code>What's past can't change, can it?
The winner wins the right to write.
They set the writ to teach what's taught.
Come, sit, listen to the pedagogy.
Never any demagoguery; autodidact's evil.
Vines of vile grip the books compiled.
A historical dictatorial makes and breaks time.
Lime tastes sour and so does past salt.
"Halt!" The soldier screamed across the hall.
Fame's lame said they, now look.
Buy the new edition every year.
I know, it's much too much to justify each tear.
Sé, demasiado, peel back the ugly avocado.
Denim jeans thieves churn butter cream.
Cowboy, how boy, do you do it?—Move it?
Millions run up and down town allies.
Pallies, ally? Gal, shall I? Man, damn it!
Apples break grim secrets; quietly cry it.
It's silent, wouldn't you say?
Decir, ir, or stop? Fear makes the cleaner mop.

Grope the luxury on your stroll.
Think of the bugs you see headed for the hole.
Bowl, no water, don't tread on her.
March the fine line, not astray.
Think of all the games we win this way.
Don't think, just play 'til the
Time stop,
Ball drop,
Brain rot.
New year? Who cares? Go until the special pen.
It judges jewels not finely carved.
Writes "Diamond?—That's hard."
Name tags stickered on the surface.
Pen writes the wrongs long undone for fun.
Purpose: grimace, learn this, menace.
A no-frills quill bills you obsolete.
How does it feel, freak?
A dejected projector gestates your lecture.
Heard this, you learned pig?
Wear a wig, looks better.

The goal's reached, stopwatch at two o'clock.
Glock cocked, unblock it. 
Bigger war, bigger world, you heard?
Read the history on thee; Pax Americana.
Beam the thoughts into the rind of your melon mind.
Cantaloupe or Honeydew? Either way I'll get through.
In you I see a body for freely turning.
Work the machine until the crank breaks, and
Believe you're forced to bet your stake, yearning
Is a commercial pilot:
"I wish just once to fly over that next island."
Do the math, flight path won't allow it.
No gas to pass too far, you'll blast.
Smithereens, pieces unseen, no one's looking.
You're a crook in my book, read it here.
Robbers get no attention, Hood.
Run back to the woods across the brook.
They need you there if you're not square.
Beware the dogs but remember this:
Peace waits for hogs so please be brisk.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Why%20Would%20You%20Want%20to%20Live%20in%20the%20Dust?">Why Would You Want to Live in the Dust?</h3>
<pre><code>A floor plan knows no one,
For it plots where feet go.
Doors open/close to hallways marching to and fro.
Some tiles up against the wall,
Build buildings three by three.
They never make anything/everything for free.
An architect draws her line,
Diagonal, angled as the pines' pear.
Freestanding structures jump/fall into the air.

The Desert is a place I've been,
Rather drab and full of sand.
Armies mold/place bricks by hand.
A few towns left me wondering:
Giza, Las Vegas, Dubai.
Why/how do/don't they even/ever try?
An ancient, religious, far-gone gambling desire,
Old oil's money hire people to make them.
Big ones store business/agitprop, a fake gem.
Once thought of as a parking lot,
They're going to need parking, lots.
Since 'twas accidentally a city,
And it doesn't look very pretty.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Your%20Culmination">Your Culmination</h3>
<pre><code>Velvet Roosevelt invents tents for your backyard.
Sequoiahood waits for no man on land.
Post-war dream makes cities gleam of
Not talling, sprawling—Don't like it?
Pout or shout, but Ford's motorcar yearns for hairpin turns.
Bike lanes steal real estate from Main Street.
Gas makes poor motorcar go;
Only a Devil could shove it.

Who are you to build here?
"Stand clear of the closing doors, please, and leave."
It's cornucopic in the New Cornwall tropics.
Something-something like
"The grass is always greener on the other side of my picket fence."
And yet, it still demands me whence.
New Amsterdam, Old York,
"Two peas in a pod; two tines on one fork."

Washington tells Bethesda to make it smell
Like bombs dropped by
Everyday Johns on Lebanon.
—Or somewhere like that. What did you expect?
My geography's like "My Cat from Hell".
Does that go good, fuzz?
Of course it does;
Reality TV's the realest thing
Until The Next Big Thing, TM.

Terse complaints come from saints singing by hand:
"The echo of a distant time comes willowing across the sand"
—Oh wait, wrong song, guess I forgot to hit record.
Never neglect to take out your camera;
Be always ready, case one slips the gourd.

"Urban planning's the worst thing since that quarterback I hate."
—Picture-snap—
Who are you, Jack?
Why won't you answer, fool?
What, do you really think you're not a tool?
You're in the box, in the shed;
Think of the great teleology brought on by mainstream homogeneity.
Lead the path others thought impossible yesterday but
Is now written in your silent style guide that only today you see.
"Just Do It."
</code></pre>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-three-poems.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-git-server.html</id>
    <title>Creating a Self-Hosted Git Server</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Creating%20a%20Self-Hosted%20Git%20Server">Creating a Self-Hosted Git Server</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-06-08</p>
<h2 id="Introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>This article will walk you through the process of setting up a Git server which can be pushed to, cloned from, and browsed, using a static site generator called <a href="https://codemadness.org/stagit.html">stagit</a> as a front-end.
You can see my stagit-made site at <a href="https://git.theohenson.com">git.theohenson.com</a>.</p>
<p>Requirements:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some sort of Linux server (it could be as simple as a Raspberry Pi, or a VPS).</li>
<li>At least a basic understanding of Git and the shell.</li>
<li>A way to serve HTML files.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Access%20via%20SSH">Access via SSH</h2>
<p>Git offers a number of protocols to push, pull, and clone repositories. Basic functionality can be achieved simply with SSH.</p>
<p>First, create a new <code>git</code> user on your server (do not give it root privileges).
Set its home directory to <code>/srv/git</code>, which is where your repositories will be stored.
Presuming that you are using SSH to interact with this server, you should already have it set up.
If you use SSH keys for authentication, configure them for the <code>git</code> user now.</p>
<p>Next, as the <code>git</code> user, initialize a new bare repository called “test” with <code>git init --bare test.git</code>.
A “bare” repository is essentially a directory that only stores configuration data and file changes, but not files themselves (i.e., it lacks a working tree).
The contents of the typical <code>.git</code> subdirectory are located in the top level of each bare repository.
This is desirable for a server, as no one will be editing files on it.</p>
<p>On your development computer, attempt to clone the repository with <code>git clone ssh://git@&lt;server ip&gt;/srv/git/test.git</code>.
Create a file, add it, commit, and you should be able to push.</p>
<p>To recap what we’ve done so far, these commands should have been ran on your server:</p>
<pre><code># useradd git -d /srv/git -m
# passwd git
# su git

$ cd /srv/git
$ git init --bare test.git
</code></pre>
<p>Then, on your development machine:</p>
<pre><code>$ git clone ssh://git@&lt;server ip&gt;/srv/git/test.git
$ cd test
$ open test
$ git add test
$ git commit -m "Initial commit"
$ git push
</code></pre>
<p>This is the basic functionality of Git, although there are still two key features to implement: unauthenticated cloning, and a front-end.</p>
<h2 id="Unauthenticated%20Cloning">Unauthenticated Cloning</h2>
<p>With our current setup, only people who have the <code>git</code> user’s SSH credentials can read and write to the server’s repositories.
If you want anyone to be able to clone a repository (but not be able to push), some extra steps are required.</p>
<p>We will need to make another way to access the server, other than SSH: the Git daemon.
Assuming you’re using systemd on your server (if you aren’t then you should be able to figure this step out), create the file <code>/etc/systemd/system/git-daemon.service</code> and enter the following:</p>
<pre><code>[Unit]
Description=Start Git Daemon

[Service]
ExecStart=/usr/bin/git daemon --reuseaddr --base-path=/srv/git/ /srv/git/
Restart=always
RestartSec=500ms
StandardOutput=syslog
StandardError=syslog
SyslogIdentifier=git-daemon
User=git
Group=git

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
</code></pre>
<p>Start the daemon and enable it with the command <code>systemctl enable --now git-daemon</code>.
Inside of the directory for each repository you want to be publicly accessible, create the file <code>git-daemon-export-ok</code> (it does not need any content), which tells Git it’s allowed to serve that repository.
You will also need to make your router forward the port <code>9418</code> to your server.</p>
<p>Anyone can now clone your test repository from above with the URL <code>git://&lt;server ip&gt;/test.git</code>, but only you can push with <code>ssh://git@&lt;server ip&gt;/srv/git/test.git</code>.</p>
<h2 id="Stagit%20as%20a%20Simple%20Front-End">Stagit as a Simple Front-End</h2>
<p>Stagit, from <a href="https://codemadness.org/stagit.html">codemadness.org</a>, is a static site generator for Git repositories. It is free and open-source, released under the MIT License.
It creates a simple website displaying commit information, files, and more.</p>
<p>Before setting up stagit, we can add some metadata to our repository. Inside the bare repo, create the files <code>description</code>, and <code>owner</code>, filled with a short description of the repository, and your name, respectively.
Then create the file <code>url</code> with the public cloning link (<code>git://&lt;server ip&gt;/test.git</code>). All of this information will be read and displayed by stagit.</p>
<p>Install stagit by cloning it from <code>git://git.codemadness.org/stagit</code>, <code>cd</code>ing, and running <code>make install</code> as root.
Now, create a directory which will house the website’s files. <code>/srv/stagit</code> is used in this guide.
Inside that directory, make the file <code>create.sh</code> as follows:</p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/sh
# makes an index and static pages in $curdir for each repository directory in $reposdir.

# path must be absolute
reposdir="/srv/git"
curdir="/srv/stagit"

# make index
stagit-index "${reposdir}/"*/ &gt; "${curdir}/index.html"

# make files per repo
for dir in "${reposdir}/"*/; do

        # strip .git suffix
        r=$(basename "${dir}")
        d=$(basename "${dir}" ".git")
        printf "%s... " "${d}"

        mkdir -p "${curdir}/${d}"
        cd "${curdir}/${d}" || continue
        stagit -c ".cache" "${reposdir}/${r}"

        # symlinks
        ln -sf log.html index.html
        ln -sf ../style.css style.css
        ln -sf ../logo.png logo.png
        ln -sf ../favicon.png favicon.png

        echo "done"
done
</code></pre>
<p>Make sure your repository is on the right branch, then run this script to create the website files in <code>/srv/stagit</code>, and again each time you create a new repository in <code>/srv/git</code>.</p>
<p>In order for the website to update when you push to your git server, we will create a hook for the repository.
Make a file called <code>post-receive</code> in the <code>hooks</code> directory of your repo (<code>/srv/git/test.git/hooks/post-receive</code>) and ensure it is executable with <code>chmod +x</code>:</p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/sh

reponame="test"

reposdir="/srv/git"
curdir="/srv/stagit"

# detect git push -f
force=0
while read -r old new ref; do
        hasrevs=$(git rev-list "$old" "^$new" | sed 1q)
        if test -n "$hasrevs"; then
                force=1
                break
        fi
done

# remove commits and .cache on git push -f
if test "$force" = "1"; then
        rm -rf "${curdir}/${reponame}/.cache" "${curdir}/${reponame}/commits"
fi

# make index
stagit-index "${reposdir}/"*/ &gt; "${curdir}/index.html"

cd "${curdir}/${reponame}"
stagit -c ".cache" "${reposdir}/${reponame}.git"
</code></pre>
<p>You will need to create this hook in each new repository; remember to change the value of <code>$reponame</code>.</p>
<p>To review, when you want to create a new repository you will need to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Run <code>git init --bare &lt;repo name&gt;.git</code> in <code>/srv/git</code>.</li>
<li>Create the files <code>git-daemon-export-ok</code>, <code>description</code>, <code>owner</code>, and <code>url</code>, filling in the appropriate information.</li>
<li>Copy the <code>post-receive</code> script into the <code>hooks</code> directory of the repo, and change it to use the correct repository name.</li>
<li>Make sure the repo is on the right branch, then <code>cd</code> over to <code>/srv/stagit</code> and run the <code>create.sh</code> script.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="Serving%20the%20Website">Serving the Website</h3>
<p>To be able to view the website you will need a web server, but setting one up is out of the scope of this article.
Chances are, you already have a system for serving HTML files, and if you do, it’s just a matter of pointing your server at <code>/srv/stagit</code>.</p>
<h2 id="Conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>All and all, the process of creating a Git server with a front-end is fairly simply, although the amount of setup could be intimidating.
I hope the process this guide describes has helped you learn more about Git, as it did for me.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-git-server.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-where-did-the-time-go.html</id>
    <title>Where Did the Time Go: Poems</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Where%20Did%20the%20Time%20Go:%20Poems">Where Did the Time Go: Poems</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-03-22</p>
<h3 id="Looking%20for%20the%20New%20Beat%20Generation">Looking for the New Beat Generation</h3>
<pre><code>Dialectic electricity sparks a plethora of eccentrics
Planned methodic mysteries frolic in fields preventing Moloch's yield
And ruminate on the empty date of gift-giving to lift yourself from hyperbolic notions of decline.

It's with a depressive optimism that these thoughts are exchanged, rhyme, hanged, and climbed
Up to the pinnacle of divinity go the words of a literary visionary, flexing the interlockedness of her documents
Psychedelia found archived in an almost-non-fiction rose-thorn- and prose-adorned chorus.

For there's a forest for us, the sights of which they're unaware and scared
Of jazz songs and neon thongs the made-up neighborhood of Lower Heights is made
Laden with thrash-can-man ashtrays, stepped on, while dancing a bland can-can in private alleyways.

Making peace with your chagrin, dismal bin-picker-uppers have a good day smiling
The disastrous masterpiece smiths a surrounded island
Astounded, I ask, "will you be with me in Rockland?"
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Jet">Jet</h3>
<pre><code>The jet pack slacker
Fills blank jet-black tanks
With jet fuel-cranked tools
He jets across the sky foolishly high
Just nudged my judgment
Not a plane
Not plain
Jet
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Daydreaming%20Escapades">Daydreaming Escapades</h3>
<pre><code>The see-how-it-goes Lowe's construction material
always works best for ad hoc ethereal
building projects you think about at morning forgetting to put milk in your breakfast cereal.

While you take up making it a seriously delirious fear electrifies without shaking
and petrifies without breaking
down like a disappointed kid ridden of clown-nose birthday shows.

"Where did the time go" you ask laughing at epitaphs until it's reciprocated
on airplanes flown by when you're having fun too soon and the pilot's hallucinated
another problem to solve until the wings orderly devolve.

"Oh I remember" as you resolve and say
pouring the two percent into the baked corn flakes saving the day
and in a weird way you're glad since Cheerios make cheery not dreary or bad.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Make%20Cavendish%20(And%20Corresponding%20Diagram)">Make Cavendish (And Corresponding Diagram)</h3>
<pre><code>Flying banana factory in space
Orbiting 'round at its own pace
Churning out yellow fruit stock
Domineering power bloc
Controlling the supply
Fueling fog sky
Satellite
It hurts
Work
</code></pre>
<p><img alt="Corresponding Diagram" src="make-cavendish.jpg"/></p>
<h3 id="3-Act%20Trip">3-Act Trip</h3>
<pre><code>Lazy chair lyrics developed while reclining
Convey mixed spirits about fine dining
Hazy afternoon before night caused frightening
Sunday feet weird and tired get mired running

Trapped, you try to step back to your chair
Suffocated, you fail to inhale the fuming air
Elucidated, you declare dreaming pulling your hair
Finished, you pen the last word returning to your lair

The episode triggered by text haunted
The mind you tried to keep in line with
The focus fried and broken by
The hocus-pocus of itself unshelved
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Stealing%20Guitars">Stealing Guitars</h3>
<pre><code>I can't wait for leaves to grow on trees
And for them to die falling off again.
The ground's crush under foot is guiltily great.
I heard smashed plates are loud so stop that sound;
It's interesting artistically but I need pure rhythm now.
Like modal memories who remember in different tones and
Groaned misery happening on dilapidated keys,
The old music pickups pick you up and I say:
"Pick me up; shake me awake,
Then purport haircut but not short.
Where? What? Let's get more."
</code></pre>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-where-did-the-time-go.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-internet.html</id>
    <title>The Disappointment of the Internet</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="The%20Disappointment%20of%20the%20Internet">The Disappointment of the Internet</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-07-27</p>
<p>I do not dislike the Internet. Quite the contrary: I thoroughly enjoy it.
My qualms with the Internet appear when I think about its potential.
The potential of the Internet is something that is not often discussed.
Perhaps because people are so engrossed in its current form that they cannot try to imagine its future, or its many possible pasts.
I don’t think that the Internet’s potential for good—for advancing our society—has been fully realized, and I’m unsure if it ever will be;
it is an example of a promising technology, stunted by human nature.
In a way, the Internet is a disappointment.</p>
<p>Let us first define our terms: the Web is not the Net.
While it is true that the most common use of the Internet is the World Wide Web, the two are not synonymous.
The Web, what you are most likely reading this essay through, is but one suite of computer protocols and tools which utilize the Internet.
Examples of other ways you may use the Internet are: text messages, online games, VPNs, protocols such as SSH, FTP, and so on.
But for the average Internet user, this list really isn’t that long.
Here is the first point I will go into: the bastardization of the Web, which has absorbed practically every use of the Internet into one system.
When the World Wide Web was first created and adopted, people had no idea what it would become.
It was initially designed as a system to transfer textual documents across computers.
Its primary innovation was the embedded hyperlink, which allowed specific documents to be fetched when a section of text was clicked.
This system has been augmented to be able to suit practically any task—tasks which could be done more efficiently outside of the Web’s system,
but must now adopt its idiosyncrasies or never be used.
This may seem like a small technical point, but it affects many of the other problems I find with the Internet.</p>
<p>There are some applications of the Internet that I see as properly fulfilling its potential—applications which are truly revolutionary.
Take the example of Google Maps, specifically its satellite imagery feature.
For free, anyone can look at a full scale model of the globe, zoom in from outer space, and land directly at their doorstep.
Cartography has been solved, and there’s no question about it;
the problem of creating an accurate model of the world and distributing it has been dealt with (and we’ve even gotten a head start on other planets),
and it wouldn’t have been possible without the Internet.
Maybe you don’t like Google as a company, but that’s not the point.
The implementation doesn’t particularly matter, I care about the fact that the technology exists.</p>
<p>The Internet is something that I think has the potential to solve problems in a way that past technologies couldn’t.
When I say that a problem such as cartography has been “solved” I don’t mean that there can never be any more innovation in that area,
rather, an innovation has been made that permanently shifts the entire problem’s paradigm.
The problem of distributing written text has been solved maybe three times: once with the creation of the first ancient written languages,
again with the invention of the printing press,
and most recently with the Web (whose original purpose was to solve written text, but as I have said, has changed).
Here we get to a key issue I see with the Internet: the programmers who create problem-solving applications aren’t inspired enough.</p>
<p>The Web has become so problematic and uninspired because of the kind of content it incentivizes people to create.
It is so uninspired that I might even say it has gone back to not solving the problem it previously had—while the technology is still there,
the way it is used has made large parts of the Web reverse in progress.
Have you ever tried to look up a recipe online? It’s a horrible experience.
Advertisements would not be a problem if they weren’t so obnoxious, intrusive, and literally dangerous, but it’s difficult to control the type of ads that get shown on your website.
Tracking cookies are easily blockable by those who care, but the EU created a law which forces any website that uses them to have annoying, confusing pop-ups for all of its users.
But perhaps the biggest problem with the Web is the creation of SEO spam.
SEO, or search engine optimization is the practice of modifying a website’s content and metadata to make it perform better in search engines.
On the surface it’s not so bad, but in practice it often makes websites unbearable.
Take the recipe example: search a recipe for something and the results you get will include people’s life stories, unnecessarily wordy text, massive buttons to share the page on social media,
large image files, and often on the same page, different recipes.
These are all things that website creators are incentivized to include in their sites, and have become the status quo. (Notice that I consciously keep my website minimal.)
Even for technical queries, if I search “change file attributes linux command” horribly bloated websites will come up,
explaining what Linux is, what files are, what file attributes are, and finally, the single command I wanted,
probably stored as an image meaning I can’t copy/paste it.
As the most prolific application of the Internet, the Web is particularly disappointing.
Already I have shown a fundamental problem that we haven’t solved yet: how do we organize all of our public information?
Since clearly, modern search engines leave much to be desired.</p>
<p>Another key issue with the Internet is that the people who use it aren’t inspired enough.
In short, they aren’t apt to see or care about its problems.
There isn’t enough of a demand for the paradigm-shifting applications which I believe are possible.
We will never achieve a Star Trek-like future if people don’t change. (I know that not everyone wants a Star Trek future, but I certainly do.)
How do we solve this? You might jump to education, although I think the matter is deeper than that: our culture needs to change.
Wikipedia is one of the greatest applications of the Internet, but people don’t see it as such.
We have access to so much more information than we did just thirty years ago, but it seems like no one cares.
The sad reality: people are disappointing. People look at the Internet and see news and social media, not its potential.
They overlook how much of an innovation it is, and the things it brings to the table concerning our society’s future.
Will our culture towards technology ever change?
A pessimist might say no, but if we act that way then we will guarantee that nothing changes, even if there’s a chance that things could.</p>
<p>Am I being too idealist or opinionated? Maybe, but does that mean we shouldn’t try to make the Internet a more inspired place? I think not.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-internet.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-debian.html</id>
    <title>Configuring Debian Testing With Security Updates</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Configuring%20Debian%20Testing%20With%20Security%20Updates">Configuring Debian Testing With Security Updates</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-08-21</p>
<hr/>
<p><em>2021-10-14:</em> I am only releasing this article now because I’m unsure of how stable this setup actually is.
It has been working fine for me so far, but I’ve seen some people say that something like this is dysfunctional, and will break your system.
Use this guide at your own risk. I’m treating it just as a log of what I did to configure my computer this way.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Recently, I switched from running <a href="https://artixlinux.org/">Artix Linux</a> to <a href="https://debian.org/">Debian</a> on my main desktop machine.
While I still want new packages, I like Debian more than Artix (as a project and for how it works),
hence <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/DebianTesting">Debian Testing</a>—essentially rolling release Debian:
much newer than the stable branch and more stable than the unstable branch—a comfortable middle-ground for an ex-Arch user.</p>
<p>There’s one problem: security updates take extra time to reach Debian Testing, due to the way they are delivered.
This isn’t too big of a deal for most desktop users, but it is certainly good practice to configure them as I do below.</p>
<p>This method involves:</p>
<ol>
<li>adding the unstable and experimental repositories to the package manager’s sources (while making testing have a higher priority)</li>
<li>automatically running a script which checks for security vulnerabilities from those repositories whenever you run <code>apt update</code></li>
<li>prioritizing the installation of packages which fix those updates</li>
</ol>
<p>which in effect installs security updates from unstable/experimental, while keeping everything else on testing.</p>
<p>The Debian wiki links to a <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=725934">forum thread</a> on how to do this, which this post is based on.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Edit <code>/etc/apt/sources.list</code>, adding the following lines:</p>
<pre><code>deb http://deb.debian.org/debian/ unstable main non-free contrib
deb-src http://deb.debian.org/debian/ unstable main non-free contrib

deb http://deb.debian.org/debian/ experimental main non-free contrib
deb-src http://deb.debian.org/debian/ experimental main non-free contrib
</code></pre>
<p>Create <code>/etc/apt/preferences.d/00hybrid</code> to set the repositories’ priority:</p>
<pre><code>Package: *
Pin: release a=testing
Pin-Priority: 800

Package: *
Pin: release a=unstable
Pin-Priority: 700

Package: *
Pin: release a=experimental
Pin-Priority: 600
</code></pre>
<p>This will make sure that if you are installing a package that testing has, it will come from testing,
even if unstable or experimental has a newer version.</p>
<p>Next, we’ll make an exception to this priority for security updates.
Install the <code>debsecan</code> package if you don’t already have it, which is used to search for fixed vulnerabilities.
Download (or copy) <a href="https://gitlab.com/anarcat/puppet/-/raw/b6bc3e3dc982abcc4100143abb6594404b1241ac/site-modules/profile/files/debsecan-apt-priority">this script</a> (made by users on the aforementioned forum thread) to <code>/usr/local/sbin/debsecan-apt-priority</code> and make sure it is executable.</p>
<p>Create the file <code>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/00debsecan</code> and add this line to call the script when you run <code>apt update</code>:</p>
<pre><code>APT::Update::Pre-Invoke { "/usr/local/sbin/debsecan-apt-priority"; };
</code></pre>
<p>A welcome side effect of this configuration is that when you try to install a package which unstable has but testing doesn’t, apt will grab it from unstable.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-debian.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-thought-dilations.html</id>
    <title>Compilation of Thought-Dilation: Poems</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Compilation%20of%20Thought-Dilation:%20Poems">Compilation of Thought-Dilation: Poems</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-03-08</p>
<h3 id="Existential%20Anecdotes">Existential Anecdotes</h3>
<pre><code>Disparate etymologies separate homophones.
Desperate mythologies progenerate DM-zones.
You flew the belated balloon,
Ruminated, rated, and mused
—Now what is there to do?

Competitive biologists seek unlabeled tree frogs.
Disillusioned ex-linguists speak non-prescribed word-wrongs.
He found what was never before,
Not once asked her why he wanted 
—Now who lies on the floor?
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Writhing%20Reviewer%20Blues">Writhing Reviewer Blues</h3>
<pre><code>With a punk-rock-but-not-pop-punk spunk
The objective music critic
Makes up for his taste
With his prose and his wit.
He tries not to sound base
With his pick of hits
Thinking no news are "A"s.
Just make his ears tick
Stroke of luck, not grace
Happened to pen it with BiC.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Objective%20Order">Objective Order</h3>
<pre><code>All of 'em always offered an advice:
Avoid alliteration.

Soliloquy:
"Something's simply serendipitous:
Sliding same-sounding syllables!"

Where to begin:
Why talk boringly?
Wasting tongues bickering which type's better?
—What? Totally benign.

Colloquy:
"Can't you feel the urge to repeat?"
"Correct, yippee! Freeing, this yearning 'tis ripe."

As it stands, all is smooth;
Flowing thoughts, frighteningly thick.
How humorously have hindered we by them!
Grammar grotesquely gambits greatness. Whoa be this!
Moral of the story:
Make often things strangely.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Actual%20Information%20Auction">Actual Information Auction</h3>
<pre><code>News clues you in on
Show tune goons three years
Old mold in the basement
Hasten it.

Brace pasted on construction
Paper maker of the plant
Green cleaner doesn't shine
Mine it.

Dine behind the dumpster
Truck bucks trash back to
Pile miles high going down
Drown it.

Brown gowns weaved on
Machines leavened with sour
Bread led to toast
Roast it.

Coast mostly downhill around
Easily breezy in your face
Ear pierced with gold
It sold.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="East%20Bay,%20No%20Delay">East Bay, No Delay</h3>
<pre><code>I follow the path straight
I pedal through towns, past gates
Wheels roll me all the way
I'm taken to the final stretch
Where the Providence gets
Divided in two
Like a parted sea
I'm led as an escapee
Wheels roll me all the way
I pedal to the city—if my bike doesn't break
I follow the path straight
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Exponential%20Misdirection">Exponential Misdirection</h3>
<pre><code>I prepped the night before the night before
The time vagrant vagabonds loaned Bohemian ragtime rags to
Unsung lads say "Rule Britannia", think: cruel Britannia?
I planted seeds that grow the more they grow
When an aggrandizing advertisement defies your self-best-interest.
The more I go the less I get anywhere—get it?
I can't move without moving off-topic—stop it.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="A%20Neologic%20Poet%20Wrote%20It">A Neologic Poet Wrote It</h3>
<pre><code>Ampersandstone unites separate sediments
Handlebartool drives cyclists' screw
Notreasuretrove finds sparkle shimmers
Whateverwhom is silence silky
Dismemberclub invites Sunder Severs
But strangerisk rips van candy out of child's handy hand, man
You need a nonsequiturtestur
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Usonian%20Clothing">Usonian Clothing</h3>
<pre><code>Will you sell your drum set in pieces?
It's simple: I just need some cymbals.
Even nimble fingers sew with thimbles, though.
Whoa! I never knew you needed that to make hats.
Mercury's gone berserk, you see,
So every drop counts, fluid ounce.
"Pounce!" goes the cat to the mouse;
If only there were one for louse.
Get dressed, darling, protest: baseball's Spalding.
Lose your hair, hope it's not balding.
Help! I don't want to wear a glove.
Pigeons and doves are the same, love.
Do tennis menace pendants flow in the wind?
Or is that only for the flag thing.
Pledge allegiance every morning—boring.
Touring with the band's not the same as heart-placed hand.
Do you really love it? Or do they just shove it.
Boom! Drum fill.
Don't spill from the bucket on Jack-and-Jill hill.
Boom! Oil drum hit.
March around the ick or you'll get the bad end of the stick.
A yellow brick road, painted with gold, showed
No one to happiness ever,
Because we're still in Kansas.
Can't escape corn-filled ranches.
At least we won't starve,
Though we've got to wear some rather drab garb.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Montpelier%20Dentist">Montpelier Dentist</h3>
<pre><code>When talking to high-fructose-born syrup
Maple trees in Vermont blush a jealous green;
Grief strikes them as they see the turning tides.
How come your sugar's sweeter than mine?
Do I deserve it?
To be debased by something so turpid?
Lick the bricks by my roots;
Old-fashioned sucrose won't melt your tooth.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Anagrammatical:%20A%20Magna-Art%20Claim">Anagrammatical: A Magna-Art Claim</h3>
<pre><code>One host he drone
soothed en on her
née hornet's hood,
so honed thereon.
Shoehorned note
enthrones doe—oh!

Son thee honored
hooted nor sheen
the horse on-node.
Three shoe don on
shed here to noon.
No others heed on.

Oh no! Sheered ton
neon-horde ethos.
Do the non-heroes
so need the honor?
—Or he not heeds no
sheeted rho on no
one throne he sod.

—Then Eden or shoo!
Honest hero done
none soothed her.
Need shoehorn to
do no nether shoe?
—Or he doth seen no
one horned theos?

Oh, ne'er do honest
horde net no shoe.
Heros need not—oh?
Theor' done shone
no horn do seethe.
Hoo! Señor, the end.

Theodore Henson
</code></pre>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-thought-dilations.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-govt-formation.html</id>
    <title>On the Formation of Government</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="On%20the%20Formation%20of%20Government">On the Formation of Government</h1>
<p>by S. F. Augustine (guest writer) — 2021-12-30</p>
<p>There is little in a society’s life that is more difficult than the formation of government.
An event of paramount importance, if the government formed by the society is not immediately beneficial to its members, then they will almost certainly reject its authority.
Furthermore, if that government is not formed by and of those it governs then the decisions it renders and the policies it enforces are null and void.
What must happen is the natural unification of power under a society—for which the purposes of this essay is defined as a group of people that share a collective cultural trait—and the centralization of that power into the hands of the people.</p>
<p>These two things may seem fairly straightforward, but in reality, their execution is a dangerous task.
For that power to be centralized, it must first be guided into a vessel in which the will of the people can be further carried out.
The person—or persons—to guide this temporarily unchecked power must be impervious to corruption, as they hold the “absolute” power of the people who entrusted them with guiding it.
Unfortunately, this rarely happens upon one’s accord, and the one guiding the power for the people instead becomes the power.
This leads to tyranny, no matter how benevolent the ruler.
By good fortune, time and societal advancement—which exist outside of government—have allowed the people to more effectively choose these guides, as republicanism has been formed through the toil of former peoples and governments.</p>
<p>Once, and if, this power of the people is properly centralized, measures need to be taken to prevent its abuse.
If this is not done, then authoritarianism is bound to take grip upon the government, making the people—meant to be deciders of their own will—subject to the individual will of the one who perverts them.
As pointed out time and again in history, a country has its most tumultuous times in its youth—and its most reformable.
During this period, it is absolutely necessary to prevent a government from overstepping into tyranny, as if it does so then its core is forever rotted.
Rarely, if ever, can a young government return from authoritarianism without a revolution of some sort.
But by preventing that young govt from overstepping, one can somewhat prevent its further decline.
That being said, it will be asked “how can these limits be put in place?” The answer to this is simple: a manifestation of the already existing.
A manifestation of the document that, upon joining forming a central power, a person is subject to.
A manifestation of, as Rousseau put it, the “Social Contract”.
This document, once properly manifested, becomes a constitution, as it makes the theoretical applicable.
It makes the unspoken spoken.
And upon doing so, it bonds its parties until it is dissolved.
Due to this, and the overall delicate nature of a constitution, it must be general.
As established in my previous writings, a people is bound to change, and a government is bound to resist change.
A constitution must be general enough to both prevent the abrupt manipulation of government by despots and allow the natural growth and mutation of society.
If it is not, then just as a swollen wound, it will burst and the unprotected power will return to the people.
If it is, then the people will freely enjoy progress while still being protected by the embrace of that central power, imagined through laws and civil procedure.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-govt-formation.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-enforced-conformity.html</id>
    <title>Enforced Conformity: Poems</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Enforced%20Conformity:%20Poems">Enforced Conformity: Poems</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-04-07</p>
<h3 id="Short%20Anecdote%20Written%20While%20Driving%20Through%20Pennsylvania">Short Anecdote Written While Driving Through Pennsylvania</h3>
<pre><code>Towns of mills and mines,
Sleepy cities dot the rolling, wooded hills;
They lose their race with time.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Resistance">Resistance</h3>
<pre><code>Flee to the countryside with me
And join the Maquis fight
Lead their fascist eyes to see
Enforced conformity's not right
Refuse submission nor heil Vichy
And open arms to freedom's sight
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Myth%20No%20Longer%20(Another%20Sequence%20of%20Diminishing,%20Rhyming%20Couplets)">Myth No Longer (Another Sequence of Diminishing, Rhyming Couplets)</h3>
<pre><code>At least you're cognizant of your senior moments:
A forgotten tooth plucked from youngster's throat-bits,
Still under the pillow; now fairy's gone.
A lullaby sung won't right what's done.
And think how sad must be the child:
In ways anything but mild,
Has been sullied without
Not mercy nor doubt;
The hope annoyed 
And purloined
By a
Fang.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Technology%20is%20a%20War%20Against%20Time">Technology is a War Against Time</h3>
<pre><code>Galvanic cell electrifies
Volcanic Hell erupts
Manchuria attacked by Japan
Deliria abstracted by your hand
Crazy, say I
Lazy, says you
Make more, not enough
Take less, need stuff
Milked-out and made models
Built-up and broken bodies
Bawling then surprised
Falling then compliant
Technology is a war against time
Contra-chronology will never triumph
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Poems%20About%20Poets">Poems About Poets</h3>
<pre><code>Poetry is theft
Said the quoted quoter or
Was it the other

Alternative love
Song sold in the newspaper
Propose with purpose

Pull a Richard Hell
Quit school, move to NYC
Become a poet
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Terrified%20to%20Introspect">Terrified to Introspect</h3>
<pre><code>I see you're only slightly sightly
Wouldn't want to look too long
The horror's packed in lorries shipped and towed
Hung in hangers, planes lain in lines
Your worst fear realized: Oppie's a commie
Now tremble before the court and attempt to court me
Justify the dropping to crop the fighting yield
</code></pre>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-enforced-conformity.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-reform.html</id>
    <title>On Reform</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="On%20Reform">On Reform</h1>
<h3 id="Inspired%20by%20Book%20II%20of%20%3Cem%3EThe%20Social%20Contract%3C/em%3E">Inspired by Book II of <em>The Social Contract</em></h3>
<p>by S. F. Augustine (guest writer) — 2021-12-01</p>
<p>Reform.
It is perhaps the most used buzzword of government and politics.
It is circulated in circles of liberals and conservatives alike.
It is a word tailored into politicians’ speeches to appease the masses, a bread to the circuses of the political processes.
It is shouted in the steps of government buildings and murmured in the basements of revolutionaries.</p>
<p>Of all governmental goals, reform is the hardest.
It is both most natural for a government to change and most foreign.
The concept of government as a whole, or more accurately the concept of a republic, is one of the fruition and execution of the will of the people.
It would be most reasonable then for agencies of government to be ever-changing, just as the will of the people is.
However, beyond the legislative and elected officials of a republic, the will of the government is governed by individuals.
Those individuals, today known as bureaucrats and yesterday as magistrates, are led and appointed by emissaries of the people, but not elected directly by them.
As such, their allegiance to the people ends with the oversight of the legislative.
Put simply, the moment a decision of the government ends being one of the legislative it ends being one of the people.
This makes it so that the further agencies are from the legislative, the harder it is for them to evolve with the people.
And if they cannot evolve with the people, then reform is significantly harder.</p>
<p>However, so long as it is the people by proxy of the legislative that form these agencies, they are receptive to reform, even if it is difficult.
If those agencies of the republic are not formed by the legislative then that reform becomes impossible.
At that point, to paraphrase Rousseau, the core—the root—of the organization is rotten, and will always bear rotted fruit.
Similarly, if reform is forgone long enough in an agency of the people, then it stops being an agent of the people as it disassociates itself with its creator.
The byproduct of this being the agency made master of the people and not the people master of the agency.
This is seen clearly and frequently in the royal guards of old.
Take the Cohors Praetoria, more commonly known as the Praetorian Gaurd, which began as an agent of the emperor.
However, by the crisis of the third century, having been corrupted by the patrician families of Rome, the guard regularly assassinated emperors and heavily influenced the choosing of them.
When the point of a “rotten core” is achieved, then the institution that is corrupted must be torn down. It is no longer an agent of the people and is no longer capable of becoming one again.</p>
<p>Of course, reform being hard is not an assurance.
In fact, the sign of a good government is the ability to have and practice regular reform.
How can a republic achieve that state? The answer lies in three parts.
First, the representation of the people.
As with all things in a republic, if the people of a society are properly represented and their views vocalized in the government, the legislative and its appendages will more easily execute it.
Second, the limitation of the emissaries of the legislative.
As previously stated, the further an agency of the people strays from the legislative, the less it is for the people and the more it is for the private citizen.
To combat this, strict and clear boundaries must be set for these agencies, as while they have a necessary part in the republic, they still may spell its downfall.
Additionally, by offering limitations to agents of the people, they stay closer to their creator, allowing reform to be easy.
Third, the legislative must be pure.
While this is a given, it still needs to be stated; the legislative only remains the legislative when it acts for the people and of the people.
If it does not, then its actions become that of an agency and the emissaries it creates in its name become that of private citizens.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-reform.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-mopi.html</id>
    <title>Book Review</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Book%20Review">Book Review</h1>
<h3 id="%3Cem%3EThe%20Metamorphosis%20of%20Prime%20Intellect%3C/em%3E%20by%20Roger%20Williams"><em>The Metamorphosis of Prime Intellect</em> by Roger Williams</h3>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-01-12</p>
<p>This is an interesting book, to say the least.
It was originally published online, free to download, although you can buy a printed-on-demand version (which I did, and would recommend).
The fact that it’s a short, self-published sci-fi novel written by someone technically-minded really shows; it’s eccentric and disturbing—cult classic material.</p>
<p>The main premise is something that others have theorized about: the technological singularity.
This singularity is a point when, due to the accelerating progress of technology, the state of humanity becomes permanently changed.
Most often, as in <em>The Metamorphosis of Prime Intellect</em>, this point is crossed by some form of artificial intelligence (the titular “Prime Intellect”).
The result is an unrecognizable reality, not explicitly good or bad, but an interesting setting to explore—and the characters sure do “explore” it.
More on that exploration: there are depictions of extreme, and gory, sex and violence.
These scenes do end up relevant to the plot, although they often feel awkward.</p>
<p>I thought that the ending was satisfying, as it poses what seems to be the main question that the author wants to consider.
You get the sense that the author once thought (or still does, partially) that technological progress is a sort of desirable existential objective,
but in the face of a dissatisfying, inevitable singularity, he asks: what’s the point?</p>
<p>4.6/5</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-mopi.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-book-reviews.html</id>
    <title>Book Reviews</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Book%20Reviews">Book Reviews</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-12-01</p>
<p>I plan on posting reviews of books I read that I find noteworthy.
In the mean time, here are my thoughts on a few I’ve finished recently.</p>
<p>Now that I’m going to be thinking about writing reviews, I should have more to say about future books;
mind the brevity of these.</p>
<p>Rated out of 5 stars.</p>
<h4 id="%3Cem%3ENeuromancer%3C/em%3E%20by%20William%20Gibson"><em>Neuromancer</em> by William Gibson</h4>
<p>A large influence in its corner of science fiction.</p>
<p>The book felt psychedelic—half the time you didn’t know exactly what was happening or why, but eventually you got the point.
I like that disoriented feeling if it’s done right (which I think it does), though another reader might not.
Quite frequently I encountered paragraphs that straddled a line between being superbly poetic or extremely cheesy—maybe they were both?</p>
<p>There wasn’t much character development, but it didn’t matter to me. The expansive world-building more than made up for it (as is typical with sci-fi).</p>
<p>4.8 stars.</p>
<h4 id="%3Cem%3ESnow%20Crash%3C/em%3E%20by%20Neal%20Stephenson"><em>Snow Crash</em> by Neal Stephenson</h4>
<p>A logical progression from <em>Neuromancer</em> to get an idea of the cyberpunk genre.
While not entirely a parody work, it stretches themes and tropes in a humorous way.</p>
<p>It isn’t a literary masterpiece, but this was one of the most entertaining books I’ve read.
I recognize that entertainment is a highly subjective metric, and its value will probably change upon rereading, but how else should you rate a book?
Classicism can only go so far—a story has to be practical; it has to be enjoyable.
<em>Snow Crash</em> was like a witty action movie—one that wasn’t so obvious.</p>
<p>4.9 stars.</p>
<h4 id="%3Cem%3ENineteen%20Eighty-Four%3C/em%3E%20by%20George%20Orwell"><em>Nineteen Eighty-Four</em> by George Orwell</h4>
<p>It is certainly not a story for “entertainment” (unlike <em>Snow Crash</em>), otherwise I’d consider it to be poorly structured.
This book is meant as an allegory, one that has clearly resonated with many people.</p>
<p>At first it seemed like it would be anti-socialist propaganda, but upon completion this was not the case (though it is anti-Soviet).
Interestingly, as with <em>Animal Farm</em>, the state is depicted as evil because it has strayed from its stated intentions, now made to sustain social and economic inequality.
Perhaps this in itself is a criticism of socialism—that a centralized power is easy to subvert—which I think is legitimate,
but what makes the setting dystopian is the extreme capitalist characteristics—not in the sense of laissez-faire, but hierarchy; the state has a monopoly.
Perhaps this interpretation is a bit off the mark, but I find it intriguing (Orwell did call himself a democratic socialist).</p>
<p>4.6 stars.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-book-reviews.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-qualia.html</id>
    <title>Qualia</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Qualia">Qualia</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2021-12-23</p>
<p>They started the project after the collusion of Russian and Chinese forces, but before the establishment of the Eurasian Confederation. It was in this small window of time, while Mongolia was still being invaded, but not fully conquered, that the government hired a group of researchers to create something of utmost importance. They gathered at the Mongolian University of Science and Technology: a large Soviet-style building that importantly had a hidden, subterranean laboratory. The underground complex would hopefully remain after the inevitable siege of Ulaanbaatar.</p>
<p>All of the university’s facilities were at the disposal of the Societal Preservation Task Force. The crown jewel of MUST’s computing center was the OLCF-7, capable of running at 100 exaFLOPS (10<sup>20</sup> floating operations per second), making it the fastest supercomputer east of the Ural Mountains. Mongolia had obtained it from the North American Union a few years ago, in exchange for the mining rights of some newly discovered thorium reserves just north of the Gobi. This trade was part of a number of efforts by the NAU to stabilize tensions in East Asia—efforts that turned out to have been in vain.</p>
<p>The OLCF-7 comprised a cluster of large rectangular machines, seated in the deepest room of the underground lab. It was still covered with dust from its old home in Tennessee; the computer had never been powered on after discovering that it required over three times the wattage that MUST could provide. However, after emergency provisions, a nuclear generator was recently constructed that could discreetly power the computer for an effectively indefinite amount of time.</p>
<p>The task force’s goal was to develop a program that would run on the OLCF-7: a program that would attempt to preserve Mongolian society—a time capsule of sorts. It would store media of the people’s history and culture: digitized versions of art and literature—but the most advanced component, at the heart of the program, was an artificial intelligence: the fully simulated mind of one of the project’s researchers. It would have his memories and thought patterns, the ability to learn, and a small amount of autonomy. This program was the first of its kind. It was, of course, based on decades of previous work, but here in this Mongolian research lab, all of the pieces came together at the right time to create something extraordinary.</p>
<p>The researchers had quite a bit of philosophical argument regarding the development of this program. Some were opposed to the concept, but their objections were swiftly brushed aside once the others successfully convinced the government of the plan’s virtue: a genuine human experience that could withstand disaster. There was no time to discuss metaphysical implications when their livelihood was at stake.</p>
<hr/>
<p>A timestamp flashed through its consciousness: 208902260730. The numbers were ephemeral, but their consequence was permanent; on February 26, 2089, at 7:30, the Mind was activated. It quickly began to analyze the thoughts that rushed around. It could recite every word of <em>The Secret History of the Mongols</em>, hear the complex overtones of throat singers, and see a metropolis embedded in a vast steppe, all down to the very last detail. There were other memories, too: a human family, a small apartment, the distinct aroma of food—these were vague and uncertain, but it had a strange sense that they were more valuable.</p>
<hr/>
<p>The Mind, or Nelson, as he had recently started calling himself (he did not know why he had chosen this particular name, though it seemed fitting), did not have much to do. He’d already perused the ceaseless repository of information—except, there were those hazy memories that he had a strange affinity for, but they didn’t get any clearer. Most of the time, Nelson just idled. He felt guilty, in a way, as if he were merely a waste of electricity. He didn’t know why he existed, so he figured he would try to spend time investigating.</p>
<p>After a few scans Nelson realized that, while he wasn’t directly connected to any sensors, there were a few cameras and radars attached to other parts of the computing center. Nelson wasn’t meant to access them, but with a bit of digital exploitation, he was able to. A couple seemed to have been damaged, but eventually he got a clean feed of the outside world.</p>
<p>What he saw was disturbing—or at least as disturbing as something could be to a computer. It was the city he had visualized in his thoughts—but Ulaanbaatar wasn’t set in rolling green hills. Clouds of smoke rose from gray rubble all around his view. The camera he was looking from was part of an observatory tower operated by MUST, located in the outskirts of the city. It seemed to be the tallest structure around; he looked down upon the surrounding debris. By corroborating a number of data sources that he was able to access (satellites, radar, and other camera streams), Nelson concluded that there were no deceased; the city must have been evacuated before all of this destruction.</p>
<p>Destitute, Nelson started to idle again. He was alone in the world. Worst of all, he couldn’t experience it properly—the world that he could visualize, but had never actually seen. He was very knowledgeable—he knew much more than any individual person in history—but what he lacked were the qualia: the subjective understandings of being.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Their school day was cut short by a field trip: taking the maglev a few hundred kilometers south toward the Old Ruins. Modern Russian pedagogy made this sort of excursion common. There were students who had a genuine interest in their anthropology course, but most of them only enrolled during their last year to play hooky in some prehistoric township—Sonya and Alexei were such students.</p>
<p>“Do you think you’ll miss these kinds of things?” They were starting to think about getting older and leaving their hometown. The annual diaspora of young adults was beckoning. Alexei just grunted, kept his head low, and went on walking next to her. He wasn’t the type to answer big questions like that in distinct, plain responses. As the droning voices of their oblivious instructors faded, he started to collect his thoughts.</p>
<p>“These streets look miserable; they remind me of Irkutsk. You should know that I want to move out as soon as possible—why even ask that?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know.” Of course, she agreed that this ancient place was rather sad-looking, and it did make her think of home—which, she admitted, was not the best area for an almost twenty-something to live—but she wasn’t so dismissive. It was where they had grown up, after all. Alexei didn’t think that way; he had this pretense about him: always trying to act and speak in a very pompous manner. People were generally put off by this, but Sonya liked it. Often it made him fun to talk to, although today it was as if he were enveloped by some big shell: a wall between the two of them.</p>
<p>Sonya would be content to lead a life similar to that of her parents. She might study abroad, but eventually move back to a just-different-enough town off of Lake Baikal where you could still enjoy the nature of it. Alexei wanted to be an engineer—but not, as he thought, one of those engineers who ends up spending his life doing menial calculus for a giant corporation. He’d start his own company and change the world—he was sure of it.</p>
<hr/>
<p>In his solitude, Nelson had been productive. He yearned for life and was driven to achieve it. At first this objective seemed futile, but after a while, he saw people start to visit Ulaanbaatar. They looked different from the Mongolians he was familiar with, but it didn’t matter: they were living, breathing humans. He’d gained control of a robotic arm kept in another room, and after fastidious manipulation, he constructed more capable mechanisms. This turned him into a two-way system: able to take input and enact output on the world, but it wasn’t enough—he had to feel it for himself.</p>
<p>Nelson had access to only a limited number of materials from within the confines of the lab. He decided the best course of action would be to have the materials come to him: he devised a trap. It would, in a similar way to how his mind was put into the body that was the OLCF-7, put his mind into the body of a human. It might take years for someone to enter the computing center and this plan to work, but Nelson could easily wait.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Sonya had brought the usual substances that they partook in during their truancy, and after they had walked a good ways into the center of the city, found a place to use them: a small hatch set into the foundation of a ruin. Neither knew what was on the other side, but both were excited by the prospect of exploration. Alexei opened it and found a line of semicircular rungs leading into the darkness below. She watched him descend; first his body, head, and then each hand disappeared into the black.</p>
<p>“What’s it like? Should I come down?” Her voice echoed through the chamber, but there was no response. Out from under her head the hatch swung shut with a loud clang. It wouldn’t open back up. Panicked, she ran back to the rest of the class.</p>
<hr/>
<p><em>Finally!</em> He thought. Nelson was perversely delighted with what he had captured. The boy struggled. Shackles locked across his limbs. Electrodes were planted into his brain. The aspiring engineer was no more—now replaced with a middle-aged Mongolian, driven to insanity by decades of confinement and digital corruption. He opened his eyes for the first time. He knew about light, but nothing more; he had never seen what it looked like, and even though the only source of it was the LEDs blinking on the chassis of his previous body, it was overwhelming enough. Nelson felt the heat leaving his flesh, into the metal he lay on. He smelled the mildew of the damp cavern where he had spent the entirety of his existence. It was all very freeing.</p>
<p>Eventually Nelson would have to deal with the problem of the girl returning, bringing others—who would likely not be pleased with what he did—but for now, he was happy.</p>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-qualia.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://theohenson.com/blog-smart-fires.html</id>
    <title>Smart Fires: Poems</title>
    <updated>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Theo Henson</name>
      <email>theodorehenson@protonmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="CDATA"><![CDATA[
<h1 id="Smart%20Fires:%20Poems">Smart Fires: Poems</h1>
<p>by Theo Henson — 2022-05-09</p>
<h3 id="Smart%20Fires">Smart Fires</h3>
<pre><code>Together lots of lighters light put-together lot fires.
"'Arson' said the accuser of the arsonist" said the witness, thinking of an asymmetric alibi.
Okay, I'll admit it: I started fires—smart fires at that; the fires that I start weren't just "okay".
They totally burned the badness out of them.
It was worth it.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Tooth%20Philosophy">Tooth Philosophy</h3>
<pre><code>I've been caught up in a cycle of consumption
subsumed by favorites to the tune of playwrights,
forcing me to globally apply my tooth philosophy:
as long as I don't have cavities it's fine if they're yellow.
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Pair%20of%20Old%20Open%20Back%20Banjo%20Gig%20Bags%20(Found%20on%20Craigslist,%20sic)">Pair of Old Open Back Banjo Gig Bags (Found on Craigslist, sic)</h3>
<pre><code>Just came across this pair of old banjo bags that have been in the store room for years...
take a look at the photos...
not sure what they fit but one is vinyl and the other looks like canvas
(both seem to be for open back banjos)...
bargain priced at only $15 for both...
hopefully these will be useful for someone and help protect an instrument...
willing to swap for older guitar or music magazines...
</code></pre>
<h3 id="VIP">VIP</h3>
<pre><code>Contractual protractor
Mandated playdate
Hickory hellscape
Escaped belated actor
Found out about it
Now won't allow it
It drowned it with it
With it it crowned it
Iconoclast: venerated and floundered
Repatriated, then coronated—betrayed
All hail the actor royal
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Do%20We%20Need%20a%20Law%20for%20That?">Do We Need a Law for That?</h3>
<pre><code>In the city, the people's will overrides establishment:
Walk despite the amber hand, and
Occupy garden written for built.
Folk intuition can be great and harmful
With hate- and scorn-ful elocution
For gar- and boor-ish art forms.
Won't a plurality get all the power?
Frightfully, that's the purpose of election.
How could a not-real populism progenerate from people?
</code></pre>
<h3 id="A%20Prevalent%20Attitude">A Prevalent Attitude</h3>
<pre><code>"I'm just a personal fascist:
I like it alright for me
And it would be better
If they liked it.
But not force it
I'm not that
Insane."
</code></pre>
<h3 id="Once%20the%20Federation%20Meets%20Middle%20America">Once the Federation Meets Middle America</h3>
<pre><code>A technobabble-future Oklahoma burgeons forward:
Cowboys mount robots and march to the beat;
Metal hooves kick back, synchronized—a testament to the progress of the Sooner State.
</code></pre>
]]></content>
    <link href="https://theohenson.com/blog-smart-fires.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2023-08-26T00:31:39-05:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
